Luigi Lucioni Papers
Luigi Lucioni Papers
1927-1964
Lucioni, Luigi, 1900-
3 linear ft.
Papers of the Italian-American painter, etcher, lithographer. Collection includes correspondence, original drawings, 237 lithographic proofs, exhibition material, photographs of work, and printed material.
149143
Biographical History
Artist Luigi Lucioni, son of Angelo and Maria (Beati) Lucioni, was born in Malnate, Italy, on November 4, 1900. He came to the United States in 1911 and later studied at Cooper Union Art School (1916-1920) and the National Academy of Design (1920-1925). A painter of portraits and still lifes, he is famous for his lithographs of Vermont landscapes.
Mr. Lucioni is represented in the Metropolitan Museum of Art, Whitney Museum of American Art, Denver Art Museum, Nelson Gallery of Art, Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, Nebraska State Capitol, Canajoharie Museum, Phillips Memorial Gallery (Andover, Massachusetts), Library of Congress, London's Victoria and Albert Museum, Williams College, New York Public Library, Carnegie Institute, Seattle Museum, Zaneville (Ohio) Museum, Dartmouth College, Hamilton College, and High Museum (Atlanta, Georgia).
He was awarded the Tiffany Medal, 1928; Allied Artists Medal of Honor, 1929; National Arts Club Prize for flower painting, 1939; First Popular Prize at Biennial, Washington, 1939, 1941, 1949; Purchase Prize, Library of Congress, 1946; First $1,000 prize, Second National Print Exhibition, New York, 1947; Purchase Prize N.A.D., 1959.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Luigi Lucioni Papers contains correspondence, original drawings, lithographic proofs, exhibition material, photographs of work, and printed material. The collection is divided into five series.
Correspondence is alphabetically arranged. Among the correspondents are Dwight D. Eisenhower and Mrs. (Frances) Henry Fonda.
Subject file consists of exhibitions in which Lucioni participated. There are 20 photographs of Lucioni's portraits, landscapes, and still lifes. Also included is a check stub of the Popular Prize won by Lucioni in 1939 as well as his statement when informed of the award.
Manuscripts and original drawings consists of nine oversize drawings, some of which are ink drawings as well as crayon and charcoal. The drawings are alphabetically arranged by title.
Proof before letter, consists of 237 proofs, dating from 192[ ] to 1965, pulled from individual plates etched by Luigi Lucioni. Many of these proofs are oversize. The proofs are alphabetically arranged by title.
Published material consists of an article, dated 1951, and clippings dated 1955 and 1957.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Lucioni, Luigi, 1900- Archives.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Etchers, United States.; Italian Americans.; Lithographers, United States.; Lithography, American, 20th century.; Painters, United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Exhibition catalogs.; Lithographs.; Photographs.; Artists.; Etchers.; Lithographers.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming, 1927-28; 1932,; 1934,; 1936-1937,; 1939-1942,; 1946-1948,; 1956 (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Exhibits, 1934-1936; 1955,; undated (Box 1)
  - Photos, 1930; 1938,; 1943,; 1945,; 1947-1948,; 1951-1953,; 1955-1956,; 1958,; 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - "Ethel Waters," Popular Prize, 1939 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Original drawings
    - [Barnyard Perspective], Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - The Birches, 1940; Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - [Dog Asleep], Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - [Dogs], Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - [Irrigation Project], Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - My Feet, Luigi Lucioni, Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - [Nude], Crayon drawing (Oversize 1)
    - [The Road], Ink drawing (Oversize 1)
    - [Tree], Charcoal drawing (Oversize 1)
- Proof before letter
  - Apple Orchard
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - [Barn and Silo]
    - #1A (Box 2)
    - #1B (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Barn and Hills, 1957
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Barns in October, 1957
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Barns in Winter, 1942
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Between Birches, 1947
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2A (Oversize 1)
    - #2B (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Beyond the Elm-Library of Congress, 1943
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Beyond the Pine, 1963
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - The Big Elm, 1934
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - The Big Haystack, 1947
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Big Shadow, 1951
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Big Willows, 1948
    - #1A (Oversize 1)
    - #1B (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
  - Birch Group, 1944
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Birch Grove, 1960
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Birch Processional, 1950-51
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - The Birches, 1940
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
  - Birches Over Pine, 1964
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Classic Pastures, 1942
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Clouds Over Manchester, 1941
    - #1 (discard) (Box 2)
    - #2A (Box 2)
    - #2B (Box 2)
  - Cypress Path, 1957
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Dominating Tree, 1964
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Edge of the Birches, 1957
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Elms, 1954
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Elms by the Lake, 1937
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Elm on the Hill, 1948
    - #1A (Box 2)
    - #1B (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Enveloping Shadows, 1965
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #1A (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Farm in the Hills, 1936
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Hilltop Elms, 1955
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Italian Courtyard, 1939
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Judson Tower, 192[ ]
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - Lake Pastures, 1938
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Lake through the Locust, 1936
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Late Shadows, 1944
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Leaning Silo, 1939
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - L. I. Farm Yard
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - Lombard Street, 1939
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
    - #5 (Box 2)
  - [Luigi Lucioni]
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - [Messina], 1945
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
    - #5 (Box 2)
  - [Messina], 1949
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Moving Shadows, 1941
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2A (Box 2)
    - #2B (Box 2)
  - My Birthplace, 1939
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Nestled Barns, 1949
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - New England Pastoral Barns, 1941
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - On the Road, 1952
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - On a Vermont Highway, 1962
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Pattern of Trees, 1944
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Peace in the Valley, 1940
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Peaceful Pastures, 1941
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Pillars of Vermont, 1937
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Pine and Birches, 1958
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - The Pine in the Birches, 1958
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
    - #4 (Box 2)
  - Restful Ruins, 1946
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Rhythm in White, 1961
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Romantic Ruins, 1949
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Route 7, 1946
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Shadow and Substance, 1944
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Shadows Across the Road, 1945
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - [Silo], 1941
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - The Spreading Maple, 1947
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
    - #4 (Oversize 1)
  - [Steeple]
    - #1A (Box 2)
    - #1B (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
  - Steeple in the Mountains, 1946
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
  - Stones and Shadows, 1950
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - The Street
    - #1 (Box 2)
  - Strong Sunlight
    - #1 (Box 2)
    - #2 (Box 2)
    - #3 (Box 2)
  - Summer Shadows, 1946; Prize in Library of Congress
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
  - [Sun Streak], 1943
    - #1A (Box 3)
    - #1B (Box 3)
    - #2A (Box 3)
    - #2B (Box 3)
  - [Sun Streak], 1953
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
  - Three Gruces, 1950
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
    - #4 (Oversize 1)
  - Three Trees, 1963
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
  - Tree Rhythm, 1953
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Trees and Shadows, 1957
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
    - #4 (Box 3)
  - Two Silos, 1942
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
  - Tree Group, 1962
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
  - [Trees]
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2A (Box 3)
    - #2B (Box 3)
  - Trees and Mountains, 193[ ]
    - #1 (Box 3)
  - Tree in Fairway, 1942
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
  - Vermont Landscape, 1931
    - #1 (Box 3)
  - First Vermont Etching (Oversize 1)
  - Vermont Pastoral, 1939
    - #1 (Box 3)
  - Vermont Survival, 1959
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
  - Weathered Barns, 1948
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
  - Whites and Shadows, 1948
    - #1 (Box 3)
    - #2 (Box 3)
    - #3 (Box 3)
    - #4 (Box 3)
  - White Arabesque, 1952
    - #1 (Oversize 1)
    - #2 (Oversize 1)
    - #3 (Oversize 1)
- Published material
  - Article, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1955; 57 (Box 3)